## **Alexander Carlson**

(281)725-8056 | www.linkedin.com/in/alex-carlson-meche/ | adcarl91@gmail.com

# **Objective**

I am a highly motivated and creative mechanical engineer, with experience in mechanical and electro-mechanical design. I use engineering first-principles and a hands on approach to break down problems and design products that fulfill the needs of the end user.

## **Education**

### The University of Texas at Austin - 3.91 GPA

**May 2024** 

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering, Engineering Honors Program Minor in Computer Science

# **Work Experience**

### Mechanical Design Engineer, Shield AI

**August 2024 - Present** 

- Delivered novel solutions for ground support equipment to refine an operator's user experience. Owned multiple projects from conceptual design through release to manufacturing in an ultra-fast paced, startup environment
- Designed an integrated power supply solution to increase available power to the aircraft and other ground support equipment by 200% while improving operator ergonomics and manufacturability. Ensured the product maintained an IP67 rating and could operate in temperatures up to 55 °C
- Designed, built, and programmed a test stand for load and cycle testing carbon fiber aircraft ducts. Created a guide for its use by manufacturing technicians
- Led electrical harness design for ground support equipment, modeling harnesses in CAD and creating manufacturing drawings using RapidHarness
- Worked directly with manufacturing engineers and technicians to create repeatable manufacturing processes
- Rapidly prototyped and built a pneumatic launcher to enable aircraft launch at max gross takeoff weight

### Mechanical Design Technician, Applied Research Laboratories: UT

**November 2023 - June 2024** 

- Designed essential tooling, jigs, and fixtures utilizing SolidWorks, optimizing the assembly process for acoustic projector assemblies used in underwater vehicles
- Employed GD&T principles and tolerance stack analysis to draft engineering drawings while ensuring precision and adherence to build quality standards

#### **Equipment Engineering Intern, Texas Instruments**

May 2023 - August 2023

- Designed fiber optic sensor mount for use in harsh chemical environments and replacing a discontinued part
- Programmed dynamic models to monitor tool conditions, preventing thousands of dollars in product scrap

## Honors Summer Internship, Applied Research Laboratories: UT

**June 2022 - December 2022** 

- Developed an autonomous unmanned surface vessel (USV) for testing marine autonomy engines
- Utilized skills in mechanical design, SolidWorks modeling, electrical wiring, and software to create mounting solutions, integrate navigation controllers, and tune PID loops for improved response.

# **Engineering Projects and Leadership**

## Texas Combat Robotics, Mechanical Design Lead

- Led rapid design process and SolidWorks modeling to construct a 15lb combat robot in a 5 week span
- Utilized engineering analysis and DFM principles to design a robust and maintainable robot

### Corporate Affairs Officer, UT American Society of Mechanical

• Managed and grew the corporate support network for UT ASME with proactive communication and outreach

## Skills

3D Modeling: SolidWorks, Siemens NX, Fusion360, OnShape

Design for Manufacturability: 3D printing, CNC machining, laser cutting and etching, sheet metal design

Programming: Python, Java, Matlab, Swift